MICHELE CLAIBOURN

I am a research director – a senior data scientist, political scientist, community-engaged scholar, and senior administrator - with 20 years of experience teaching, leading, and managing research and data science teams. Recently I've been building and leading Research Data Services⁷ in the UVA Library.

My own work has turned towards action-based research, using the tools of data science to promote accountable governance², make visible racial and other social inequities³, and impact public policy and movement building. I am always interested in opportunities to use my experience and skills towards creating a more economically and socially just world.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Current 2015

Director, Research Data Services & Social, Natural, and Engineering Sciences

UVA Library, University of Virginia

- · Lead Data Scientist, Equity Center, 2020-present (partial buyout)
- · Faculty Affiliate/Lead Data Scientist, Global Policy Center, 2019-present
- · Co-Director, Community Policy, Analytics & Strategy Lab, 2018-present

2015 2013

Director, StatLab and Research Data Services

UVA Library, University of Virginia

· Associate Director, Data Science Institute, 2014-2016 (partial buyout)

2013 2011

Data Scientist

Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, University of Virginia

2011 2004

Assistant Professor

Department of Politics, University of Virginia



EDUCATION

2002 1996

PhD., Political Science

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, WI

1993 1989

B.A. Political Science

Rice University

OHouston, TX



♣■ TEACHING AND MENTORING

2020 2002

Graduate Courses

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

· Public Interest Data Lab, Saving Lives with Data, Text as Data, Applied Causal Inference, General Linear Models, Linear Models, Applied Time Series, Mixed-Effects Models/Longitudinal Analysis, Introduction to Statistical Analysis

2020 2002

Undegraduate Courses

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

· Project First Gen +, Research Design & Analysis, The Presidency and the Public, Media & Political Communication, Political Pscyology & Decision Making, Citizen Competence in American Democracy, Introduction to American Politics

2019 2013

Select StatLab Workshops⁶

University of Virginia

· Six-part series on Data Science in R, Multiple Imputation, Cluster Analysis, Duration Models, Matching Methods, Mixed-Effects Models, Sentiment Analysis, Topic Modeling, Text Classification, Data Wrangling, Linear Modeling

CONTACT

- @ mclaibourn.github.io
- github.com/mclaibourn

linkedin.com/in/mclaibourn

See full CV and project portfolio at mclaibourn.github.io.

Leadership

Consult with researchers and design research projects with partners seeking to better understand racial disparities and social structures, and to develop a policy response.

Founded StatLab⁴, a data science consulting service for members of the UVA community where I continue to serve as a senior consultant and to mentor student fellows.

Build a new division of the library enhancing our ability to support the growing data science research community at UVA, recruiting, hiring, and managing a team with diverse skills and talents to meet emerging university research needs.

Supervise a team of 10-12 fulltime staff, 3-4 graduate fellows, and research teams across mulitple collaborations on a range of research projects, including work on equity and COVID response in the Charlottesville community, racial disparities in the local child welfare systems, forced displacement events with humanitarian partners, and additional communityoriented and library-directed data science efforts.

Last updated on 2020-06-06.

2019	•	REU Mentor
		School of Data Science, UVA
		SELECTED PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS
2019	•	Charlottesville Foster Care Study ⁷
		Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services
		· With Charlotte McClintock and the Public Interest Data Lab
2019		Panel Chair and Moderator
		Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia
2019	•	Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses
		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia
		· With Paul Martin
2013	•	Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters
		Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82
		· With Paul Martin
2012		Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the Scope of Conflict
		Political Behavior 34: 27-56
		· With Paul Martin
2011	•	Presidential Campaigns and Presidential Accountability ⁸
		University of Illinois Press, Series on Democracy, Free Enterprise, and the Rule of Law
2007	•	The Third Face of Social Capital: How membership in Voluntary Associations Improves Policy Accountability
		Political Research Quarterly 60: 192-201
		· With Paul Martin
2002		Gender Differences in Citizen-Level Democratic Citizenship: Evidence from the Comparative Study of Electoral Systems
2000		Presented to the International Political Science Association (2000), the Midwest Political Science Association (2001), and the Conference on Comparative Study of Electoral Systems (2002)
		 With Virginia Sapiro 2001 Winner, Sophonisba Breckenridge Award for best paper on Women & Politics, Midwest Political Science Association Annual Meeting
2000	•	Trusting and Joining: An Empirical Test of the Reciprocal Nature of Social Capital
		Political Behavior 22: 267-291
		· With Paul Martin

Teaching and Writing

20 years of experience teaching statistics and data science methods, applied policy research, and political behavior to undergraduate and graduate students.

Design data workshop series for student and adult learning communities, including recruiting and mentoring instructors, marketing and assessment, and contributing to select topics.

Experienced writer in multiple formats, from university press books and peer-reviewed journal articles, to action-oriented reports for local and state agencies, educational materials, and informal writing.

Skilled in communicating about data, technology, and policy to stakeholders, advocates, and learners.

Methods and Software

Statistical modeling and data science
R, RStudio, Shiny
Data wrangling and visualization
Stata and SPSS
Text analytics
GitHub and reproducibility
Some Python and SQL
Qualitative methods

1: https://data.library.virginia.edu/

• LINKS

- 2: https://commpas.batten.virginia.edu/
- ${\tt 3: https://virginiaequitycenter.github.io/cvilleequity_covid/}$
- 4: https://data.library.virginia.edu/statlab/
- 5: https://data.library.virginia.edu/
- 6. https://data.library.virginia.edu/training/past-workshops/
- 7: https://doi.org/10.18130/v3-ztey-hn31

8: https://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/75hhf7en9780252035920.html			